[Music]
Hello and welcome to this session on
moving tables and fields between apps
source extensions. I'm Peter Boring and
with me today I have Satias Draonis.
So as extensions mature and the solution
change or when coming with an old
monolithic solution, a need to refactor
and optimize for separation of concern
for um breaking into modules or for
breaking into independent sellable SKUs
arise and however there's a challenge uh
with splitting up
extensions. So first of all, tables and
fields must be moved. Uh data must also
be moved. Uh the breaking changes that
follows from moving the tables and
fields must be handled. Uh upgrade code
needs to proen be written in the case uh
of a pretendant extension and up until
now this whole procedure has been
blocked for apps source apps.
However, uh in uh the previous release
uh we added the ability in the platform
uh for AL developers to move tables and
fields between extensions without
writing upgrade code. Uh that was used
in but also only allowed for the base
application in uh 2024 release wave uh
1.
However, now we also extend that
capability to publishers uh to make it
much more efficient for them to refactor
their apps source
extensions. So uh the feature uh is
supported for two kinds of extensions.
Uh as I mentioned you can use it for app
source extensions uh targeting the
runtime from uh version 150 and higher.
Uh you can also use it for onremise uh
extensions for business central on
premise version 26 uh.0 and higher. Uh
per tenant extensions are not uh
supported for this. Uh in in cloud you
can use the for sync uh and upgrade code
units uh to handle that.
So uh you might remember some five years
ago or something like that we added the
ability to migrate tables and table
extensions via a migration.json file in
the
application. However that is for moving
uh basically out of a code customized
base app to a standard base app with
extracted customizations on top and
something that was supported on premise
only. The ability that we are talking
about today is the ability to move
individual tables and fields um across
extensions in cloud in SAS with minimal
breaking changes and so it's not
intended to move all tables. It's not
efficient for that either. Um so so TS
can you tell us more about how all of
this works? Of course, Peter, let's go
and look at some of the scenarios uh on
moving fields and how this new feature
works and uh what it lets you do. So
when we talk about moving tables or
fields, what we mean is about passing
the ownership of this uh in terms of the
data so that the uh data in a table for
example is moved from one extension to
another. But we are also talking about
the ability to refer from these fields
uh through other apps. So for example,
if we move an a table from one app to
another, then you will need to have a
dependency on the destination in order
to refer to it. Let's look at a few
different scenarios. In order to
distinguish how these moves happen, we
have split the possible scenarios into
three. The first scenario is called move
down.
uh the scenarios are defined by uh the
relation between the source and the
dependency extensions. In the case of
move down the destination is a
dependency of the source. So if we look
at the graph for example here we have a
large monolith app which contains two
tables sales and inventory and we want
to split this large app into smaller
parts. So we want to make two
dependencies a sales app and an
inventory app and move the tables there.
So we can for example assign them to
different teams so they can work on
them. Another possible functionality
could be to take out common
functionality that many extensions are
using into a common dependency so that
we can use it in multiple
places. Then we have the move up
scenario. In this case it's the opposite
relationship. we have an extension and
we want to move uh the tables up to
other extensions which depend on the
first
uh the reason why we might want to do
this is for example if we have uh
functionality which is specific to a
country. If this functionality for
example was in monolith and we wanted to
split it into modules which are specific
for the each country, we can use the new
feature to move the tables to new apps
which are specific for the countries.
Here we are moving from the monolith app
the tables sales and inventory to their
corresponding apps and you can see also
the dependency relationship.
Finally, we have the more general
category, the lateral move where there
is no dependency between the source and
the destination. This covers every other
case, but uh it is a breaking change as
there is no uh dependency relationship
to maintain the relationships between
these uh
symbols. Let's look at what is possible
in terms of moving tables and fields.
When we talk about tables, it is
possible to move them from any extension
to any other extension with this
feature. When we are talking about
fields, they are all there are some
limits to where they can be moved. First
of all, fields can be moved from a base
table to a table extension as long as
the table extension has the same uh
based target table.
It can also be moved from a table
extension to another table extension as
long as they both have the same target
table. What is not supported is moving
from a table extension back to the base
table which is called consolidation
because it is not part of this feature.
Let's take a specific case. Let's go
hands-on to see how we would move a
table to a dependency to understand this
feature more.
We're going to go through a scenario
which contains a lot of elements so we
can understand how uh what are the
different stages and actions you need to
do in order to use this feature. We're
going to take the case of this large
monolith app which contains a bunch of
different objects but some functionality
based on sales and some functionality
based on inventory. We are going to
split this to make this uh our solution
more maintainable and keep the monolith
up but we're going to move the sales
specific functionality into a sales app
and the inventory functionality into an
inventory app. We are using the move
down scenario as you can see because
these new apps will be dependencies of
the monolith. Our first stop uh should
be the source code. Let's see what we
have to do for the source and the
destination. On the source extension, we
need to find the definition of the table
here table sales and we need to use
obsolution in order to mark it for
moving. We use the obsolute state
property which you will know from the
normal obsolution and use the new values
pending move and moved to mark the table
as moved. Pending move is used in order
to declare that this table will become
unavailable in a future version. The
move to property marks the destination
of our move. It needs to take the value
of our of the app ID of the destination
application. On the side of the uh
destination extension, our sales
extension or our inventory extension. We
are going to use the move from property
to mark where the this table is going to
come from. First we have to copy the
definition of our table and make
basically a copy of the original table
for this extension. It has to have the
same schema including some changes which
might not be breaking like adding an
extra field but uh the there must be no
schema breaking changes and we have to
mark it with the moved from property as
I mentioned before. This one has to
match the source extension app id. If
the two of them match then when these
apps are uh finally published, synced
and installed then the move will be
possible. If instead of this we were
moving a field then the situation is
very similar. We would just need to use
the obsolation property on the source on
the field and then we would need to use
the move from property on the
destination. So it's very simple in
terms of code.
Let's talk a little bit about the
requirements between the source and the
destination. What needs to happen for
this move to be
successful? First of all, uh the if we
are moving a table and we are moving it
to with a breaking change that is we are
moving it higher or to an app which has
no relation with the source then we need
to use obsolation. Before moving it, we
need to use the pending move property as
I mentioned
before. Then in terms of the move to
property, it must contain the app ID of
the destination extension. If it does
not, then it will not be possible to
make the move successfully because there
is validation that uh these app IDs
match. The another thing to keep in mind
is that as soon as we move out our
table, until the takeover is done, the
table will not be able to be referenced.
That means that if there are other apps
which reference it then they will uh
have compilation errors or uh errors in
the
runtime. Finally, we need to keep the
table definition in the source extension
because it is used to validate that the
move has been done properly every time
an app is
installed. Let's uh talk a little bit
about the destination. Now on the
destination we need to copy the
definition of the table as I mentioned
before without any schema breaking
changes. Again the moved from property
must contain the app ID of the source
extension and that must match because
that's what allows us to validate that
the move is correct. And finally if we
are moving fields then we can only move
them to table extensions with the same
base table. We cannot move to other
tables. If we look at the project files
for the apps then we can see uh what
change we need to do to our monolith app
in order to support this. The only
change we need to do is that in the
second version where we have done the
move we need to add the dependencies to
the uh new apps the sales app and the
inventory app. And we also need to set
the propagate dependencies property to
true in order for apps which dependent
on the monolith app to still have access
to the tables that we are moving after
the new
version. Now let's talk a little bit
about how do you deploy these extensions
after you have made the effort to create
them and to have your
extensions. Let's do a small review on
what we are trying to achieve. We are
trying to move the functionality for
sales to a sales app and the
functionality for inventory to an
inventory app. The first thing to
consider is when does a move happen.
Moves happen during the syncing stage of
an extension's life cycle. This is the
stage after publishing your app and
before installing it where the database
schema is changed in order for the new
installation code to be able to run on
it. So this is when the move will
actually happen when these apps are
deployed.
The rule of thumb to ensure success when
you are doing a move is that the source
extension in a move must be deployed
before the destination. This way it's
possible for the takeover to happen
correctly. How do you deploy it? There's
two ways. If you are a developer and you
are trying to test out your solution,
then you have to use Visual Studio Code
development for development.
And uh if you're using business central
then this is handled by business central
when uh customers install app source
extensions. Let's uh try to deploy our
apps to see how we would achieve our
scenario that I showed just a little bit
before. We start first of all with
business central not even having our
monolith app and uh we have our original
monolith app with sales and inventory
included.
If this is published through VS code and
synced then you will see that the
database contains uh a table sales and a
table inventory and they both belong to
a monolith
app. In version two of our monolith app
where we are moving them out, we use the
obsolution properties to set them as
moved. As soon as we publish and the
extension is synced, these apps are
marked as unavailable. In the next step,
we have to install our new sales app
which is taking over the table
sales. As soon as we sync it, now the
table changes ownership to the sales app
and is now available to be used and
there will be no longer be runtime
errors. Similarly for the uh inventory
app, as soon as we publish it and we
sync it, it is now available for us to
use. Let's talk about some important
details in this uh scenarios.
First of all, you don't need to make new
extensions to move tables and fields to
them. You can use existing extensions as
uh destinations as long as you publish
new
versions. The other thing to consider is
that takeover from a destination
extension is blocked if the source
extension is moving to a different
destination. That means that there is
validation that you can't take over any
table or if you give up a table then not
every extension can take it over only
the one that is declared by the source
extension. Finally, if the source
extension of a move is not published,
then new tables of fields will be
created for the destination. So if we
were just publishing the sales or the
inventory app then uh and the monolith
app had never existed never been
published on the system then new tables
would be created for the new
apps. Let's go through another case when
we have uh an app we don't just move
tables and fields but there are also
things which depend on these tables and
uh fields. Let's take this example here.
We have an multi-purpose app which
contains some functionality specific to
food items and we want to move them to a
food items module. We don't just want to
move the table food items. We also want
to move the page that shows the food
items with it. So how is it possible for
us to take this page and move it to a
different
extension? The answer depends on if this
move is a breaking change or a
non-breaking change.
If we are moving uh objects up or doing
a lateral move then it is a breaking
change and we need to do a two-step
process. The first uh thing to do is
that we need to set the obsolute state
to pending for the other objects which
depend on our table for the first
version of our app and then later we
need to remove them from the original
extension and redefine them on the
destination.
If we are moving down to a direct
dependency then it doesn't have to be a
breaking change. This we can uh handle
similarly to our previous scenario where
we can set propagate dependencies to
true on the source extension and remove
the objects from the source extension
and redefine them in the destination
which is the dependencies. Then we don't
need to do any obsolution. But we also
have the opposite situation. It can be
that we need to move a table but this
table depends on some minum for example
for the values of its fields. What do we
do in that case? How do we ensure that
the source extension and the destination
extension can work after this move? This
can be done by using a common
dependency. So in this case we have the
enum my enum that we need to have
available for both the source extension
and the destination extension. So we
extract it into a common dependency and
uh add it for as a dependency for both
the destination and the source. This way
we can keep both of them compiling and
working after the move. Now let's talk
about how you can submit your own uh
appsource uh
extensions. The process is quite
straightforward for submitting to
appsource because it handles most of the
validation automatically. The process is
to first submit the source which will
validate uh the obsolution of the apps
which of the tables which are being
moved. Then you submit a destination and
this will do the full validation for the
move to see if it is
valid. What does it mean for a move to
be valid? Let's look at what validation
subsource will perform. First of all, it
will ensure that the source extensions
for all moves exist. That means that if
you are saying that the table is coming
from a specific extension in your in the
extension that you're submitting, apps
source will
ensure that uh this extension exists and
has been submitted uh correctly and past
validation. The other validation is that
both the source and destination can
compile after the move. This ensures
that the move is valid and can
work. Also, we make sure that the source
extension is giving up the table or
field to the extension where that is
trying to take over. This prevents other
extensions from trying to take over an
incorrect uh table or field. Finally, uh
appsource validates that there are no
breaking changes in schea between the
versions of a table or a field in the
source and destination extensions. This
ensures that it is possible to sync the
app when it is uh installed and the move
can be done
properly. Let's look at some things to
think about and do before you submit
your app to ensure the success of the
move. First of all, you should set up
the move validation locally through
appsource
scope. This will ensure that your the
rules run locally and you can catch any
failures early without needing to wait
for the submission. You should also try
the move on a sandbox or a docker
container to ensure that the uh data has
the correct structure and that uh it
fits with the rest of your applications
which depend on
it. Submit the source extension first
and then the destination. If you are
moving down to a library extension, you
can put both of them in the same
submission and it will
work. Finally, consider first submitting
the source and destination in preview.
This way customers can upgrade both of
them when both are available and you
don't need to make only one of them
available. For example, the one which
moves out the table uh so that it
becomes
unavailable. How do I enable the move
validation rules locally? The process is
quite simple. Uh what you need to do is
first of all you need to build the
source extension to have a package to
use as a baseline.
You enable the appsource scope analyzer
for your project and then create a
directory in it and place this uh source
extension. By adding the new property we
have uh added for this feature and
making it point to this directory, you
will have enabled the validation and
this will allow you to test out the move
locally. Here is an example of how it
looks like in terms of the settings you
need to set.
Finally, let's talk a little bit about
the performance of this feature. How how
does it handle a large uh volume of
data? Can what can I use it for? This
feature was designed to handle a large
amount of data and to do as little
copying as possible uh for these moves.
Let's look at a few scenarios and how
performance works for them behind the
scenes.
If we are moving a field from a table
extension to a table extension, then
there is no data transfer happening. It
is just a column rename in the database.
So even if you have billions of rows, it
will it can happen instantly. It is very
performant. If you are moving a field
from a base table instead to a table
extension, then some data transfer needs
needs to happen. However, it is
equivalent to the AL data transfer
object and it is very performant as it
is done in
buds. If you are on the other hand
moving
tables, if it doesn't matter if you are
moving from an extension to a dependency
or up or doing a lateral move. In all
cases, this will be done through a table
rename in the database which will cause
no data transfer and it will be
extremely performant even for large
tables. So moving is suitable even for
very large
databases. In summary, moving tables and
fields is a feature that empowers the L
developer to refactor their extensions
to modular, more maintainable parts. You
can read more details about this feature
in our documentation uh in the links you
will find in the description below this
video. Thank you SAS. Thanks for joining
this session and staying with us to the
end. I hope you enjoyed um that we're
now enabling publishers to seamlessly
refactor their applications. Keep in
mind though that such changes u can
still have some downstream impact on uh
any uh partner that are building on top
of your solution. Enjoy the other launch
sessions. Thank you.